A Guide to the William Stephen Moss Collection, 1863-1864
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
William Stephen Moss Collection, 1863-1864
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2008-019
1 folder; 0.1 cu. ft.
Papers centering on William Stephen Moss, a Confederate prisoner of war during the American Civil War. Includes an identification card, letters from Moss to his mother, a biography written by his son, and a photograph of Moss.
Dealer
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The William Stephen Moss Collection was purchased by Special Collections in 2004.
Biographical Information
Born 12 October 1839 in Buckingham County, Virginia, William Stephen Moss became a member of the Confederate Army during the American Civil War. Moss served in the 4th Virginia Cavalry, Company B from Chesterfield, Virginia. Captured at Germana Ford on 19 September 1863 when scouting the Union Army, Moss was brought to Washington as a prisoner of war. Moss was quickly transferred to "Point Lookout" in Maryland. On 16 August 1864, Moss was again transferred to Elmira Prison in New York-a prison with a reputation for its unhealthy conditions and high rates of scurvy. On one occasion, as related in the biography of Moss written by his son, Moss attempted to escape by tunneling out of prison with common utensils; but, guards thwarted the plot. After the war, Moss opened a general store with his brother (James Knox Polk Moss) and married Cora A. Leadbetter. William Stephen Moss died in 1924.
Biographical information was obtained largely from the biography of Moss found within the collection.
Scope and Content
The materials in the William Stephen Moss Collection include information on the conditions of Northern prisons during the Civil War and Moss's personal life. Letters from Washington, DC; Point Lookout, Maryland; and Elmira, New York stem from Moss's capture at the Germana Ford in 1863. One letter predates Moss's capture. Specifically, in these letters Moss discusses his desire for a prisoner exchange, the disinterest of authorities in prisoners, endemic sickness, and the tradability of tobacco for stamps. Many original POW covers (envelopes) are included and are marked with signed approval and original postage. Also in the collection is a biography written by Moss's son, William D. Moss, and a hand-tinted photograph of an elderly Moss with a hunting dog lounging near a tree.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type. Letters appear chronologically.
Contents List
- Moss, William Stephen, 1863-1864 (Folder 1)
  - William Stephen Moss's identification card, n.d.
  - Letter from Culpepper, Virginia, 24 March 1863
  - Letter from Washington, D.C., 22 September 1863
  - Letter from Point Lookout, MD, 1 October 1863
  - Letter from Point Lookout, MD, 21 April 1864
  - Letter from Elmira, NY, 5 September 1864
  - Letter from Elmira, NY, 26 October 1864
  - Letter from Elmira, NY, 2 November 1864
  - "Biography of Wm Stephen Moss: Christian, Citizen, Soldier, Business Leader and Father" by William D. Moss, n.d.
  - Hand tinted photograph of William S. Moss and hunting dog, n.d.